<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Information for the ignorant, or, The applicatory part of a late printed book, called, A light for the ignorant containing a few observations upon the I Cor. 10, which doe strongly prove it to be absolutely sinfull to heare the word preached in any false state, or assembly, whatsoever : also a postscript containing a challenge (layd down in 9. propositions) to all the Non-conformists in Old and New England, and Holland / made by N.E.</title>
            <author>N. E.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21069</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7435.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S1911</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22914403</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22914403</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25867</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21069)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25867)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1791:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Information for the ignorant, or, The applicatory part of a late printed book, called, A light for the ignorant containing a few observations upon the I Cor. 10, which doe strongly prove it to be absolutely sinfull to heare the word preached in any false state, or assembly, whatsoever : also a postscript containing a challenge (layd down in 9. propositions) to all the Non-conformists in Old and New England, and Holland / made by N.E.</title>
                  <author>N. E.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Cloppenburg Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and publisher suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, X --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
               <term>Dissenters.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25867:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25867:1"/>
            <p>INFORMATION FOR THE IGNORANT OR THE APPLICATORY PART OF A LATE PRINTED BOOK, CALLED, A LIGHT FOR THE IGNORANT, containing a few Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. which doe ſtrongly prove it to be abſolutely ſinfull to heare the <hi>word</hi> Preached in any Falſe State, or Aſſembly whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Alſo a <hi>Poſtſcript</hi> containing a Challenge (layd down in 9. <hi>Propoſitions</hi>) to all the <hi>Non-Conformiſts</hi> in Old and New <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Made by N. E.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JER. 15.19, 20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Therfore thus ſaith the Lord, if thou return, then will I bring thee againe, and thou shalt ſtand before me, and if thou take forth the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious from the vile, thou shalt be as my mouth, let them return unto thee, but return not thou unto them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare of <hi>God,</hi> 1640.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="observation">
            <pb facs="tcp:25867:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25867:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A FEVV OBSERVATIONS OUT OF THE 1. <hi>CORINTHIANS</hi> 10.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Firſt thing to be <hi>obſerved</hi> is this, That <hi>God</hi> having committed a Kingdome or Kingly ſtate Eccleſiaſticall to <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Mediatour who is the King of it; that thoſe that he doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath or commit this Kingly ſtate unto, they are by actuall receiving of it, Incorporared into him. This the Scripture calls an <hi>ingrafting into Chriſt,</hi> Joh. 15.1. Rom. 11.24. it is called a <hi>marriage,</hi> Reve. 19.7, 8, 9. and divers other phraſes it hath to ſet it forth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that this is Simbole-wiſe ſet forth by example of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> the act that the <hi>faithfull</hi> doe, comparing it with theirs; and <hi>Moſes</hi> with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Moſaicall ſtate, and <hi>worship,</hi> with the Euangelicall ſtate and <hi>worship.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, that this <hi>ſtate</hi> and <hi>worship,</hi> it being <hi>Gods,</hi> they were only bound to it, and to no other: but ſtraitly charged to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve whatſoever he had given them in charge, <hi>and to walke uprightly</hi> in this <hi>ſtate,</hi> and in all the <hi>ordinances</hi> of the Kingdome. So that to this <hi>ſtate,</hi> muſt <hi>men flow unto,</hi> and to no other, and here to abide and not to depart.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſtraying,</hi> of the <hi>faithfull</hi> in matter of Religion in publick affaires, is called <hi>Idolatry,</hi> the which the ſervants of <hi>God</hi> muſt <hi>flee from,</hi> verſ. 14. The <hi>faithfull</hi> muſt not break the firſt Table, no more then the ſecond.</p>
            <p>The Second <hi>Obſervation</hi> is this, That as the <hi>faithfull</hi> are <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:25867:3"/>into <hi>Chriſt</hi> (that is, <hi>tyed</hi> and <hi>knit</hi> to him) ſo that <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>appurtenances</hi> goe together, I meane the <hi>priviledges</hi> of the Mediatourſhip, the <hi>priviledges</hi> of <hi>marriage ſtate,</hi> and all the <hi>appurtenances</hi> thereunto belonging, verſ. 16. and this <hi>food</hi> is for all the <hi>faithfull;</hi> ſo that as they have the <hi>true and glorious ſtate of Chriſt,</hi> ſo they have it fill'd and adorned with <hi>rich</hi> and <hi>glorious priviledges</hi> and <hi>ornaments,</hi> and that as they be <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> ſo they be <hi>precious</hi> in <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>uſe.</hi> Here is the <hi>ſeate, habitation,</hi> and <hi>dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> of the <hi>ordinances</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> theſe and none other are the things commanded to be <hi>obſerved</hi> and <hi>kept;</hi> theſe and none elſe-have the <hi>promiſes</hi> belonging to them; theſe and none other have <hi>juyce</hi> and <hi>life</hi> in them, in this <hi>ſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as here be all the <hi>ordinances</hi> of <hi>Gods publicke worship,</hi> ſo here is the <hi>appurtenances</hi> belonging to them, as State, Lawes, Offices, and <hi>adminiſtrations,</hi> with their <hi>glory</hi> or <hi>bleſſing</hi> on them.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt therfore here be the <hi>ordinances</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, they be here in their <hi>proper place.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly, they be here in their <hi>right uſe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fourthly, they ſtand here in their <hi>beauty,</hi> with the <hi>bleſſing</hi> on them, with all their <hi>attendances,</hi> and with the lively uſe of them.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Third <hi>Obſervation</hi> is in verſe 17. becauſe the <hi>faithfull</hi> are <hi>one body,</hi> or <hi>bread,</hi> or <hi>cake,</hi> they be <hi>vnited</hi> and <hi>knit</hi> together by a <hi>ſpirituall bond,</hi> or <hi>tye,</hi> even their <hi>corporation.</hi> This <hi>one-nes</hi> is ſuch that admits not a diviſion in <hi>religious acts,</hi> they be a <hi>religious ſociety</hi> or <hi>body,</hi> it is <hi>ſpiritually one.</hi> This reſpecteth chiefly thoſe that be a <hi>body,</hi> or <hi>Church</hi> (yet it is largely to be underſtood) for there is no permiſſion given to any to <hi>walke contrary to this rule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this one <hi>ſtate</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>ordinances,</hi> and <hi>priviledges,</hi> with their own <hi>appurtenances</hi> thereto appertaining, belongs one <hi>people</hi> or <hi>body,</hi> or <hi>Church,</hi> with their adherent matter adhering there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. So this one <hi>body</hi> is partaker of <hi>one bread</hi> or meanes of <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall nourishment,</hi> which is <hi>ſpirituall feeding</hi> upon the <hi>ordinances.</hi> So that as the <hi>body</hi> is <hi>one</hi> (that is) <hi>one</hi> in <hi>compactneſſe</hi> or <hi>knitting; one</hi> in Charter, <hi>one</hi> in Laws, <hi>one</hi> in <hi>ordinances, one</hi> in <hi>offices,</hi> and <hi>one</hi> in <hi>adminiſtrations;</hi> ſo it muſt be <hi>one</hi> in <hi>communion,</hi> and <hi>one</hi> in <hi>feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> on this <hi>bread,</hi> or meanes of <hi>ſpirituall nourishment.</hi> They be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>baptized</hi> into <hi>one Chriſt,</hi> by <hi>one Spirit;</hi> partakes of <hi>one calling,</hi> and of <hi>one faith</hi> and <hi>hope,</hi> as Epheſ. 4.4, 5, 6. ſo partakes of <hi>one fellowship,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.9. So that here is the <hi>open houſe</hi> that <hi>God</hi> doth <hi>keep,</hi> that whoſoever is <hi>hungry</hi> muſt <hi>come to,</hi> for ſatisfie their <hi>hunger,</hi> and not ſeek <hi>ſpirituall food</hi> any where elſe but in this <hi>ſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25867:3"/>
The Fouth <hi>Obſervation</hi> is out of Verſe the 18. where the Apoſtle layes it down example-wiſe, that ſo as in a Table or Glaſſe they might ſee the poynt in hand; and the ground that the Apoſtle layeth againſt them to diſprove, and condemne their <hi>judgement,</hi> and ſo their <hi>practiſe</hi> in <hi>eating</hi> of the <hi>Idols inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted meats</hi> (if any did ſo) this Verſe ſhews that the aforeſaid <hi>ſtate</hi> and <hi>ordinances,</hi> and all things pertaining to them, they be unſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable: ſo that thoſe that partake of the <hi>ordinances</hi> in a <hi>ſtate,</hi> partakes of that <hi>ſtate,</hi> or <hi>power</hi> and <hi>authority,</hi> by vertue of which they are adminiſtred. So that as every <hi>ordinance</hi> of that <hi>ſtate</hi> hath an <hi>authour,</hi> or <hi>inſtitutor;</hi> ſo they cannot partake of the <hi>ordinance</hi> but they muſt partake of the <hi>Altar that ſanctifieth the Ordinance to the receiver.</hi> By <hi>Altar</hi> in the New Teſtament of <hi>Chriſt</hi> is to be underſtood not any <hi>materiall Altar,</hi> as that of old: but ſome <hi>ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall thing</hi> or <hi>things,</hi> as is cleare in the Teſtament of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Now that there is an <hi>Altar</hi> in the time of the Goſpell, aſwell as in the time of the Law, is cleare by a multitude of places of <hi>Scripture,</hi> Ezek. 43.14. Heb. 13.13. Reve. 8.3. That this <hi>Altar</hi> is not <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, is cleare to me from this 8. Chapter and 3. Verſe, where he is <hi>the High Prieſt that offers up the incenſe with the prayers of the Saints:</hi> And that is not in the <hi>heavens</hi> properly, but in the <hi>heavenly ſtate,</hi> appeares by the 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. Chapters, with the whole Revelation. What this <hi>Altar</hi> is we may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of Reve. 11.1. where the <hi>Temple,</hi> and the <hi>Altar,</hi> and the <hi>worshipers</hi> are diſtinct. The <hi>Temple</hi> I conceive to be the <hi>ſtate,</hi> for that compriſeth all within it, as the <hi>Altar;</hi> the ſeverall <hi>inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions</hi> therein, the <hi>worshippers,</hi> the <hi>people,</hi> and this appeareth in the <hi>text.</hi> That this is no <hi>wordly Temple,</hi> but <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> is plain: For as the <hi>Altar</hi> is, ſo is the <hi>Temple</hi> (to wit <hi>ſpirituall</hi>) therfore the <hi>oblations,</hi> and <hi>ſacrifices</hi> be <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> the which being offered to God in, and upon this his own <hi>inſtitutions</hi> or <hi>Altar,</hi> they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come acceptable, as Heb. 10.19, 20, 21, 22. And as it is in this <hi>true ſtate,</hi> ſo it is in all <hi>falſe ſtates</hi> (that is) there is the ſame <hi>connextion</hi> and <hi>communion</hi> betwixt the things themſelves (that is) the <hi>ſtate</hi> depends upon the Lord of it, and owner of the ſame (as afterwards may be ſeen) and the <hi>inſtitution</hi> depend on the <hi>ſtate,</hi> and the <hi>ordinances</hi> depend on the <hi>ſtate</hi> and <hi>inſtitutions.</hi> So that without the <hi>ſtate</hi> no inſtitutions, and without <hi>inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> no <hi>ordinances,</hi> and ſo no <hi>worship.</hi> So alſo is the <hi>matter</hi> depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant on the <hi>forme,</hi> and the <hi>forme</hi> or <hi>ſtate,</hi> on the <hi>author</hi> of it; ſo that the <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>forme</hi> are <hi>relatives,</hi> and the <hi>forme</hi> and <hi>author</hi> are <hi>relatives</hi> alſo (that is to ſay) they cannot be ſeparated. So the
<pb facs="tcp:25867:4"/>
               <hi>receit</hi> or <hi>partaking</hi> of ſuch <hi>ordinances</hi> that are to be partaked of in a <hi>ſtate,</hi> the partakers to have <hi>communion</hi> with the <hi>ſtate</hi> and King of it, as this example doth ſhew. So that the <hi>matter</hi> is depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent on the <hi>ſacrifice;</hi> the <hi>ſacrifice</hi> dependant on the <hi>Altar,</hi> the <hi>Altar</hi> on the <hi>ſtate,</hi> the <hi>ſtate</hi> on the owner of it, and ſo cometh in here, If this were any thing to reprove the <hi>judgement</hi> or <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe</hi> of the Corinthians, then it ſheweth that by their generall <hi>communion</hi> in <hi>eating inſtituted meat,</hi> in that <hi>inſtituted ſtate</hi> and <hi>Temple,</hi> they did partake of it, even of that <hi>diabolicall ſtate</hi> and <hi>inſtitutions,</hi> though they were not of that <hi>body,</hi> but were of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and come to the Idols Temple but on oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion: yet ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>thoſe that eat of the ſacrifice of the Altar, partake of the Altar, for it is the Altar that ſanctifieth the guift to the receiver,</hi> Mat. 23.19, 20, 21. and it is the pollution of it, (that is to ſay of the <hi>Altar</hi>) that pollutes the <hi>guift</hi> or <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> and thoſe that offer it, Hoſ. 9.1, 2.4. <hi>Eating</hi> is uſed for <hi>receiving</hi> and for <hi>feeding,</hi> and ſo for all <hi>religious communion,</hi> as Act. 10.13, 14. and in this Verſe for <hi>partaking of the Altar,</hi> as well as of the <hi>ſacrifices,</hi> ſhewing that he that partakes of any <hi>adminiſtration</hi> in a <hi>ſtate,</hi> doth partake of the <hi>power,</hi> or <hi>inſtitution,</hi> by vertue of which it is adminiſtrated.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Fift <hi>Obſervation,</hi> is out of Verſe the 19. where the Apoſtle as he doth mention the ground that their <hi>judgement</hi> was built upon Chapter the 8 verſe the 4. ſo he alſo uſeth their own grounds, in their own phraſes, that ſo he might both re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove their <hi>errour,</hi> and alſo that he might ſhew the contrary. Now in that the Apoſtle ſpeaks queſtion-wiſe, it is not becauſe he made doubt of the unlawfullneſſe of their <hi>practiſe,</hi> but to ſhew the vanity of the ground of it; and to ſhew that when it is compared to the <hi>truth,</hi> and brought to the <hi>true touchſtone,</hi> the <hi>revealed will of God</hi> it vaniſheth away, though it might ſeem colourable and ſtrong: yet it being but the beame of a Spiders webbe, in regard of the <hi>truth</hi> it ſelfe, he ſhews it hath no force norſtrength in it: therfore he incluſively affirmeth that the Idol is ſomthing, and that that which is offered to Idols is ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, becauſe it alters its property to that which it was before, being now ſet apart for Religious uſes, and is not to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that he held as they did but the contrary (namely) that it was unlawfull for them to goe to the Idols Temple to eate of their <hi>meat</hi> or <hi>ſacrifice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The Sixth <hi>Obſervation</hi> is out of Verſe the 20. where the Apoſtle comes to a full anſwere affirmatively to their objection
<pb facs="tcp:25867:4"/>layd down Chap. 8.4. <hi>that there is but one God.</hi> And in it are ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry things to be obſerved: As Firſt the thing implyed in the former Verſe (to wit) it was not as it was thought, but as he plainly affirmeth in this 20th Verſe (to wit) <hi>that the Gentiles did ſacrifice to Devils,</hi> in which he ſhews what a neare relation there is between the <hi>worship,</hi> and the <hi>worshippers:</hi> the neare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction between the <hi>authour</hi> of their <hi>worship</hi> (namely the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil) and the <hi>worshipers</hi> who had communion with him. And if it be here objected this is meant of none but the Idols <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,</hi> and not of thoſe that <hi>worship God,</hi> and that with ſome glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſhew of <hi>truth,</hi> as is done in the <hi>Antichriſtian ſtate,</hi> it muſt be remembred, that if we will <hi>worship God,</hi> it muſt be tendered up to him, in his own <hi>houſe,</hi> and by his own <hi>rules</hi> and <hi>ordinances,</hi> or elſe it is not <hi>his,</hi> neither doth he <hi>accept it:</hi> neither can men truly be ſayd to do it to <hi>him,</hi> if it be done in any <hi>falſe ſtate</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, he being any the <hi>author</hi> of it, but ſome other, for he never <hi>inſtituted</hi> no <hi>ſtate</hi> for his <hi>people</hi> to <hi>worship</hi> and <hi>ſerve</hi> him in, but only <hi>one</hi> (namely) this <hi>heavenly Ieruſalem which is the mother of us all,</hi> Gal. 4.26. therfore though men that walke in <hi>falſe ſtates</hi> do pretend that they <hi>worship God,</hi> even the <hi>true God,</hi> yet the <hi>truth</hi> is otherwiſe; and this I apprehend to be cleare in this Verſe: for the <hi>Corinths</hi> would never have frequented a <hi>worship</hi> that they had knowledge of it, was done to the Devil; neither had the Apoſtle ſaid any thing to the purpoſe in ſo ſaying, had it not been ſo that they did not know that it was ſo, for they did plead for it upon other tearms, even upon morall grounds (as the Profeſſours doe for <hi>hearing</hi> in the Aſſemblies.) So then it follows undeniably, that men may pretend to <hi>worship</hi> the <hi>true God,</hi> though the <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of <hi>worship</hi> be <hi>falſe.</hi> So alſo that men in <hi>religious communion</hi> cannot ſever at their pleaſure, and put difference between the <hi>office</hi> and <hi>adminiſtration,</hi> and the <hi>ordinance</hi> and thing <hi>adminiſtred</hi> (that is) they can as they <hi>pretend</hi> heare the <hi>word,</hi> and partake of the <hi>exerciſe</hi> of the <hi>guift,</hi> and yet not partake of the <hi>office:</hi> for they doe not (they ſay) heare him as a man in <hi>office,</hi> but as a man indued with a <hi>guift</hi> to <hi>preach</hi> the <hi>word.</hi> If theſe perſons are ſo skilled in this diviſion, let them ſhew their <hi>wiſdome</hi> herein, and compare it with the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which ſaith that there is no dividing of them; ſo that as any partakes of the one (that is of the <hi>adminiſtration</hi>) they doe partake of the other (that is) of the <hi>power</hi> or <hi>office</hi> by vertue of which it is <hi>adminiſtred.</hi> For we muſt remember that an <hi>office,</hi> and an <hi>adminiſtration,</hi> is the Charriot wherin the thing <hi>admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:25867:5"/>doth ride, and were it not for the <hi>office,</hi> neither <hi>perſon,</hi> nor <hi>guift,</hi> nor <hi>ordinance,</hi> nor <hi>adminiſtration</hi> cou'd be there, to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe his <hi>guift,</hi> ſo that the <hi>power</hi> puts into <hi>office,</hi> the <hi>office</hi> into <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration,</hi> and they both put forth the <hi>ordinance,</hi> or thing <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred.</hi> Here alſo if any think that thoſe that are not joyned into <hi>followship,</hi> that they are more <hi>tollerated</hi> in this particular then others that are in a <hi>ſtate:</hi> The Apoſtle overthroweth that whileſt he ſheweth, that thoſe of <hi>Corinth</hi> that went to the Idols Temple, went as thoſe that were not in <hi>fellowship</hi> with them, for that was not all their ſin, that they for the preſent left their <hi>ſociety,</hi> but that they had taken up a ſinfull <hi>communion,</hi> both with <hi>perſons,</hi> and with <hi>things</hi> which was unlawfull. So that the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle urges the <hi>foulneſſe</hi> of that <hi>practiſe,</hi> chiefly for the unlawfull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of it in it ſelfe, which he would never have done, had not that <hi>place</hi> or <hi>ſtate</hi> bin to have been abandoned of all whatſoever that <hi>feare the Lord:</hi> Therfore this practiſe of going to Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Aſſemblies, which the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> calls <hi>whores houſes,</hi> Prov. 5.7.8. &amp; 13.14. is not onely unlawfull in the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> but alſo in all others that be in the <hi>order of the Goſpel,</hi> for what ground or warrant hath perſons to come there at all; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this is one badge and marke of our <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> to have our <hi>faces towards Sion,</hi> and <hi>our backs upon Babylon,</hi> Jere. 50.5 &amp; 51.9. and in the walking in this <hi>way,</hi> and on this <hi>ground</hi> perſons are to be held, and judged the <hi>people of God,</hi> and not otherwiſe. So that here is a ſhutting up of the <hi>controverſie,</hi> namely, that there is no more to be ſaid, but that this verdict muſt be given, <hi>even that they that had communion with the Gentiles in their Temples and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices had communion with him that the Gentiles had communion with: But the Gentiles did ſacrifice to, and had communion with Devils: Therfore thoſe that had communion with them in eating of their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice had ſo too: But it is the mind of God that all thoſe that he called by his name, should not have fellowship with Devils: Therfore of all that feare God it muſt be avoyded, which is done by us when we forſake all falſe and Antichriſtian wayes, and walke onely in God: true wayes, without halting, worshiping him in Sion the City or place of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, according to his own appointment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Seaventh <hi>Obſervation</hi> is out of Verſe the 21. where the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> doth ſhew the impoſſibility of the <hi>people of Gods par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking</hi> of the <hi>adminiſtrations</hi> both in a <hi>true;</hi> and <hi>falſe ſtate</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>rule,</hi> and without <hi>wrath</hi> it for as the former part of the Chapter doth ſhew in thoſe examples both of the ſinne of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> who though they were <hi>incorporated</hi> into <hi>one body</hi> unto
<pb facs="tcp:25867:5"/>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> their <hi>Mediatour,</hi> and <hi>type of Chriſt,</hi> whoſe <hi>lawes</hi> and <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> they were to obſerve, yet ran a whoring after their own <hi>inventions,</hi> and alſo of the wrath of <hi>God</hi> manifeſſed on them that did ſo, Verſe 5.7, 8, 9, 10. for <hi>God</hi> cannot indure any <hi>halting</hi> between him and <hi>Baal,</hi> 1 King. 18.21 neither can a man ſerve two Maſters: but as <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath purchaſed <hi>ſoule</hi> and <hi>body,</hi> with the price of his own <hi>precious bloud,</hi> ſo he will have us to <hi>glorifie him in our ſoules and bodies,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.20. &amp; 7.23. which is done by our <hi>obedience to the truth;</hi> ſo that the <hi>obſervation</hi> of theſe things themſelves be the onely things of our <hi>wealth:</hi> it is therfore the Saints wiſdome to keep them in the ſight of all the <hi>people.</hi> The <hi>Lord</hi> having ſet before us <hi>life</hi> and <hi>death,</hi> it is the wiſdome of the Saints to eſchew the wayes of <hi>death, and to have their feet guided in the paths of life;</hi> theſe things being ſo oppoſite to each other, that the imbracing of the one, is the rejection of the other; for a man cannot walke in the <hi>true wayes of God,</hi> but he muſt reject, and hate the <hi>falſe wayes</hi> of the Devill. Beſides for theſe, and like ſinnes (that is) for leaving of the <hi>pure wayes of God,</hi> and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braceing wayes of their own, the <hi>Lord</hi> removes the Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke from, and abhorres even his own <hi>inheritance;</hi> ſo that for this he forſook the Tabernacle of <hi>Shiloh the tent that he had pitched among them,</hi> Pſal. 78.60. ſo that they be unfit for <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> with him, and uncapable of ſuch <hi>heavenly treaſures</hi> as the Saints are made partakers of, that ſo do. So that <hi>God</hi> doth war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and approve of no ſuch perſons walking ſo; <hi>ſo that if there be an evill heart in any, thus to depart, or draw backe from the living God, his ſoule can have no pleaſure in them,</hi> Heb. 3.12. &amp; 38, 39. And thus I underſtand this <hi>Scripture</hi> treats of the communion of the <hi>people of God</hi> both with him as <hi>God,</hi> 1 Joh. 3. Heb. 12.23. and alſo with <hi>Ieſus</hi> as <hi>Mediatour,</hi> ver. 24. and to <hi>Ieſus</hi> the <hi>Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of the New Teſtament.</hi> The things that they have with <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> is that <hi>heavenly ſtate</hi> called <hi>Mount Sion, the City of God, the heavenly Ieruſalem,</hi> and the drawing neare to <hi>God</hi> in the wayes of his <hi>worship</hi> herein, is the drawing nearer to him in a <hi>new and living way, conſecrated by the vayle of his flesh,</hi> Heb. 10.20, 21, 22. This being the <hi>ſtate</hi> which the <hi>Lord</hi> hath <hi>inſtituted</hi> for the good of the <hi>godly,</hi> they are here to <hi>dwell under the shadow of the Almighty,</hi> Pſal. 91.1. <hi>there to lye town in peace and quietneſse</hi> becauſe the <hi>Lord</hi> is at one with them, and not to change their <hi>habitations; for all ather wayes are wayes of darkneſſe,</hi> Iſay 59.8, 9, 10, 11. <hi>and he that walkes in darkneſſe though he ſayes he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with God, he is a lyar</hi> (as ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 Joh. 1.6.)
<pb facs="tcp:25867:6"/>Seeing the <hi>Saints have received a Kingdome that cannot be shaken, yea a Kingdome</hi> with all the <hi>glorious appurtenances</hi> thereunto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing: therfore let all the <hi>Lords people</hi> have <hi>grace, whereby they may ſerve the Lord with reverence and godly feare,</hi> by <hi>walking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightly and unblameably in his wayes.</hi> Concerning the approved uſe of <hi>Gods ordinances</hi> we are taught of <hi>God,</hi> to uſe them as he hath given <hi>commandement</hi> and not otherwiſe: For in Exod 20. <hi>God</hi> ſtraitly forbids the <hi>unholy uſe of any thing that his Name is put unto,</hi> the which is done when it is uſed any other wiſe then that he hath appointed, as the whole body of the <hi>Scripture</hi> doth plainly manifeſt. Now <hi>Gods</hi> Name is largely to be underſtood, and the <hi>command</hi> is as large as the <hi>name</hi> or <hi>things:</hi> ſo that by <hi>Gods</hi> Name we are not onely to underſtand <hi>Gods Eſſence,</hi> as Exod. 3.14 but alſo his <hi>Attributes,</hi> as Exod. 3.5, 6. and alſo his <hi>Ordinances,</hi> his <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Goſpel,</hi> Deut. 33.34. Acts 9.15. as alſo the <hi>Law of Chriſt,</hi> Eſay 42.1. is called his Name, Mat. 12.21. alſo <hi>prayer,</hi> Gen. 4.26. and <hi>Gods</hi> whole <hi>worship</hi> with all his <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> partaining to the ſame, Deut. 21.5. Mal. 1.11, 12. and his <hi>Seales,</hi> Mat. 28.18, 19. and his <hi>Cenſures,</hi> 1 Cor. 5.4, 5. Mat. 18.20. So that <hi>God</hi> requires the <hi>holy uſe</hi> of all whatſoever his Name is put unto; ſo that as he doth in the firſt <hi>Commandement</hi> forbid any beſides himſelfe to be <hi>worshipped,</hi> ſo in the ſecond he requires all <hi>worship</hi> to be performed to himſelfe onely, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own rules expreſſed in his <hi>word,</hi> which containes the onely Rules for <hi>worship:</hi> ſo that, as we muſt receive them only, and <hi>worship</hi> him onely by thoſe <hi>rules,</hi> ſo we muſt uſe them as he hath required, and not after, neither our own <hi>wills,</hi> nor after any others; but to take heed that we doe obſerve to doe them, as he hath given charge to uſe them, and not otherwiſe, <hi>for he will not hold them guiltleſse</hi> that ſhall uſe them otherwiſe then he requires. So that this Law of his is the ground of all <hi>worship,</hi> even of that <hi>worship</hi> that he requires, and it inforceth the ſame, and perfectly bindes even all that will by the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> manifeſt themſelves to be the <hi>people of God</hi> to keep cloſe to it, and not to meddle with any other <hi>ſtate, ordinance</hi> or <hi>worship</hi> whatſoever, as the tennour of this Law rightly diſcerned doth manifeſt: as alſo the tennour of the New <hi>Teſtament</hi> doth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew (namely) that the <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt</hi> hath removed the Candleſtick from the Jews, and given it to the Gentiles, Rom. 9. and 11. Chapters, as alſo Mat. 22.2.7. and ſo forward, Mat. 21.43. This <hi>ſtate</hi> or <hi>Kingdome</hi> hath diverſe names in the New <hi>Teſtament,</hi> as the <hi>ſtocke</hi> of a <hi>Vine,</hi> Joh. 15. it hath the name of an
<pb facs="tcp:25867:6"/>
               <hi>Olive ſtocke,</hi> Rom. 11.24. the name of a <hi>Kingdome,</hi> Mat 21.43. Mat. 22.2. the name <hi>Temple,</hi> Rev. 11.1. <hi>City, Mount Sion, Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, the houſe of God,</hi> Heb. 12.22. <hi>a Golden Candleſticke,</hi> Rev. 2.1. This <hi>ſtate</hi> ſo diverſly named, and ſet forth, is the proper <hi>ſeate</hi> or <hi>being</hi> of all <hi>Gods publike ordinances,</hi> and <hi>worship</hi> (as the Temple of old was, ſo is this) as the 1 Cor. 10. doth ſhew, and as all the Primitive examples doth plainly prove. So that the <hi>ordinances</hi> of <hi>worship</hi> as they be placed, and ſeated there, ſo they cannot be lawfully uſed any where elſe: ſo that as <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old was tyed to the <hi>worship</hi> and <hi>ſacrifices,</hi> and <hi>feaſts</hi> of all kinds that did belong to <hi>Gods publick worship,</hi> ſo they were ſtrictly tyed (as to the <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship</hi> it ſelfe, ſo to) the <hi>place</hi> that he had choſen out of all the Tribes to put his Name in, Deut. 12.11. 1 Kin. 8. chap. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the 9.2, 3. thither to reſort <hi>at the time appointed, there to worship and ſerve the Lord, as alſo to rejoyce before him, and in his preſence.</hi> Therfore if there were in any a refuſall or omiſſion, it was a <hi>forſaking of him,</hi> and did <hi>procure his wrath,</hi> as in the 2 Chro. 29.6, 7, 8, 9. So the Apoſtle exhorts <hi>to take heed that there be not in any an evill heart in departing from the living God,</hi> Heb. 3.12. but to keep cloſe to the way of his <hi>Commandements.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing the <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſo placed his <hi>ordinances</hi> that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be lawfully removed out of his own houſe, and that all thoſe that will manifeſt themſelves to be the <hi>Lords people</hi> by their <hi>obedience</hi> to his <hi>will,</hi> muſt thither repaire for the food of their <hi>ſoules,</hi> and not to wander in the <hi>way</hi> of the <hi>ſtrange woman, ſeeing Wiſdome hath a houſe pollished, her table furnished with dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> the <hi>command</hi> and <hi>call of God</hi> to come thither, Pro. 9.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. Mat. 22.3. Cant. 1.6. and the right uſe of them, with the <hi>promiſe</hi> of <hi>bleſſing</hi> on them, 1 Cor. 10.16. and all the <hi>appur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances,</hi> that belong to them, as this 1 Cor. 10. doth ſhew. Therfore as all perſons in matters of Religion are ſtraitly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to <hi>worship</hi> any other <hi>God</hi> but the <hi>true God,</hi> ſo alſo to <hi>worship</hi> him by any other rules then what he hath layd down: ſo after no other manner then he hath preſcribed, as the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> do joyntly drive at, and may be ſeen in this 10. Cor. The which that we may a little the better underſtand, for this end, we muſt conſider that we ſpeak of <hi>Gods publick worship,</hi> and not otherwiſe; ſo we muſt oppoſe ſuch acts of Religion as are done in a <hi>publike ſtate:</hi> ſo that the ſequell of my reaſoning is not only to prove the <hi>adminiſtring, and receiving of the ſeales in a falſe State to be unlawfull,</hi> but all other <hi>actions</hi> (as the <hi>preaching</hi> and <hi>hearing of the word</hi>) or of what nature ſoever they be, being done by
<pb facs="tcp:25867:7"/>that Diabollicall oppoſite power to <hi>Chriſts,</hi> as alſo by oppoſite perſons to <hi>Chriſts ſubjects</hi> of <hi>Chriſts Kingdome:</hi> theſe perſons being <hi>powred</hi> and <hi>authorized,</hi> not by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but by his <hi>adverſary,</hi> ſo that they are <hi>functioned</hi> and <hi>officiated</hi> by the enemy of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> though for ſome cauſes to <hi>God,</hi> and themſelves they <hi>prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, theevishly,</hi> and <hi>uſurpedly intermeddle</hi> with ſome <hi>ordinances</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> for which ſin they may juſtly feare <hi>that he will shortly come in flaming fire, rendring vengeance to them for that their wickedneſſe,</hi> that though they <hi>preach</hi> his <hi>word,</hi> yet doe not know him, as his <hi>ſervants</hi> know him: and alſo for <hi>detayning the truth in unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 1.18. Rom. 1.18. So in the ſecond place I will ſhew <hi>that whatſoever power Eccleſiaſticall, and ſtate Eccleſiaſticall is oppoſite to Chriſts power, and ſtate, that that is a whore, and is by the rule of Gods word to be fled from, and none of the ſervants of God to be found therein;</hi> For the <hi>Lord</hi> calls all his <hi>elect ones</hi> from them, as from the place where the life of <hi>grace</hi> cannot breath in, and as from the Cage that is ſo <hi>uncleane,</hi> that there can be no building, or abiding there for the <hi>Lords</hi> cleane Fowles, <hi>for that's the hold of every unclean and hatefull Bird,</hi> Rev. 18.2, 3, 4. Therfore ſeeing the <hi>good word of God</hi> which is <hi>holy</hi> in it ſelfe, yet it comes to be <hi>uncleane</hi> in the uſe of it in <hi>falſe ſtates:</hi> ſo that inſtead of <hi>nourishing</hi> the <hi>ſoules</hi> of them that uſe it there, it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>does them, and is a <hi>two edged ſword</hi> to ſlay them in the true, and right ſence of it. So that thoſe vaine and frothy flouriſhes which are made by the Subjects of <hi>Antichriſts</hi> Kingdome of thoſe glorious things they have, and poſſeſſe in theſe dayes, are by the <hi>Lord</hi> reproved in his <hi>truth,</hi> aſwell as the Idols Temple, whoſe indeed they be and not the <hi>Lords</hi> So that this is it that I would prove. Firſt, <hi>that God hath given a Kingdome, and State Eccleſiaſticall to his Servants.</hi> Secondly, <hi>that this Kingdome and State is compleat with Laws, and Ordinances, with Officers and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations for the execution of the holy things of God.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>that as all that by rule would be judged to be the Lords people, are commanded of God to ſeek the place where he hath put his name, there to ſeek reſt for their ſoules; ſo alſo they muſt manifeſt themſelves to be the Lords by their obedience to the truth, in cleaving to that old, and good way that leadeth to eternall life.</hi> Fourthly, <hi>that no publike worship can be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to God out of this Kingdome, and ſtate:</hi> and that I conceive is clearly manifeſted out of this 10. <hi>Corinht.</hi> by the example of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old. Secondly, in that the faithfull in time of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell is in an eſtate more <hi>glorious</hi> then they were Heb. 10.28, 29-12.22. Therfore when the Saints come into any other <hi>ſtate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:25867:7"/>or are under another <hi>inſtitution,</hi> performing Religious actions therin, they be by the voyce of <hi>God</hi> pronounced to be Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as this 10. Cor. 7. doth ſhew. Fiftly, <hi>that the Ordinances of Gods houſe muſt not be removed out their place, which is their own ſtate:</hi> for as the veſſels of the Sanctuary were prophaned by <hi>polluted perſons;</hi> ſo alſo in the uſe of them in any other place then where the <hi>Lord</hi> had commanded them to be uſed: for they could not be uſed <hi>holyly</hi> among the Babilonians who ſet them in their Temple, becauſe they wanted their proper ſeat or place of and being all thoſe that had them when they were removed out of the <hi>Lords houſe</hi> could not uſe them but prophanely, they being not the perſons that <hi>God</hi> had appointed to uſe them, nor the place. This is plain if we conſider the tennour of <hi>Gods</hi> Book with the third <hi>precept.</hi> So that he hath compiled <hi>ſtate, laws, ordinances,</hi> with their <hi>offices</hi> and <hi>adminiſtrations</hi> together, as may be ſeen in all the Churches, and in this 10. Cor. Further; <hi>that as men muſt not partake of any of Gods ordinances but according to rule: So muſt they uſe and frequent none other;</hi> for all wayes of a mans owne are by <hi>God</hi> condemded, all <hi>precepts</hi> of men forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; therfore the <hi>ſtate</hi> and <hi>ordinances</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> with all <hi>appurte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances</hi> muſt of all <hi>Gods people</hi> be flowed and adhered unto, not to be departed from, they being the onely life of the <hi>ſoule,</hi> the <hi>wells</hi> in the right uſe of them, that the waters of life doth run in. So that by this little that is ſaid, I may be diſcerned both what I intend, and alſo the drift of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> which is, that <hi>Gods ordinances</hi> cannot be rightly uſed out of his own <hi>ſpirituall houſe,</hi> or <hi>ſtate;</hi> and that it is unlawfull for us to goe any where elſe to partake of any of them, Cant. 1.6. whether it be the <hi>Sacrament</hi> or hearing of the <hi>word,</hi> ſeeing he that partakes in any <hi>adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in a <hi>ſtate,</hi> partakes of the <hi>ſtate</hi> it ſelfe; and ſo hath <hi>communion</hi> with the Devil, the <hi>author</hi> and <hi>king</hi> of all <hi>falſe ſtates,</hi> as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle againſt the <hi>Corinths</hi> in the 10th Chap. doth ſtrongly prove by many <hi>illuſtrations.</hi> So that <hi>hearing</hi> of the <hi>word</hi> under an <hi>Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi> is aſwell <hi>communion</hi> as <hi>receiving of the Sacrament:</hi> for the <hi>ſacrifice</hi> here ſpoken of, was part of the Jews <hi>worship,</hi> and not any of their <hi>Sacraments,</hi> as the <hi>Non-conformiſts</hi> ignorantly and blindly affirme. For they had <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and the <hi>Paſſeover</hi> for their <hi>Sacraments,</hi> inſtead of which <hi>Chriſt</hi> our <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>ordinance inſtituter,</hi> ſet up for us under the Goſpell <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and the <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Now unto as many as walke according to this rule peace be unto them, and mercy, and unto the whole Iſrael of God.</hi> Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:25867:8"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>A PVBLIKE CHALLENGE MADE BY</hi> N.E. <hi>to all the</hi> Non-conformiſts <hi>or</hi> Reformiſts <hi>in Old and New</hi>-England, <hi>and</hi> Holland, <hi>in the behalfe of the totall Seperation, but in a ſpeciall manner made to thoſe perſons in</hi> London <hi>that are convinced that the Church Miniſtry and worship in</hi> England <hi>are all of them</hi> Antichriſtian, <hi>and yet hold it lawfull for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to walke in a ſtragling ſpirituall way, without joyning or uniting of themſelves to a true</hi> viſible Church. <hi>But all, and every one of you are Challenged to Anſwer theſe</hi> 9. <hi>inſuing Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions particularly in writing if you be able.</hi> London <hi>An.</hi> 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="propositions">
            <head>The firſt <hi>Propoſition.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <hi>THAT the planting of Grace in the ſoule, is not only a renovation: but it is an inſtamping ingrafting, or creating of a new creature, or a communicating of the divine nature unto the ſoule, which in no meaſure it had before, no not in Mans innocencie,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.45. <hi>to the</hi> 50. 2 Pet. 1.3, 4 For <hi>Adam</hi> in his <hi>innocencie</hi> was but a <hi>perfect morall man,</hi> and had no participation nor divine communion with the <hi>divine nature,</hi> which if he had had, he had been as <hi>perfect</hi> as <hi>Chriſt himſelfe,</hi> and could not poſſibly have fallen from his <hi>innocency;</hi> for it is the Saints <hi>communion</hi> with the <hi>divinity</hi> of <hi>God</hi> which makes them that they cannot loſe the <hi>truth</hi> of the ſeed of <hi>grace</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath wrought, or beſtowed upon their <hi>ſoules,</hi> 1 Joh. 3.6.9. &amp; 4.4.2.27. the ingrafting of which is the immediat, and alone worke of <hi>God,</hi> Joh. 3.3.5, 6. Epheſ. 2.1.4.5, 6. 1 Pet. 1.3.23. 1. Joh. 2.20.29. &amp; 5.20. 1 Cor. 2.12. wrought without the uſe of meanes.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18.21.24. <hi>Act.</hi> 27.22. <hi>to</hi> 25.34.</note> And that all that the Miniſtry of the word, or any other meanes doth, is no more but this, namely, to manifeſt, and declare, that this <hi>divine principle</hi> or <hi>nature</hi> is in the <hi>ſoule,</hi> Luke 8.5.8.15. or to build up, and <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> the <hi>ſoule</hi> in <hi>ſpiriturll things,</hi> or in the <hi>wayes of God,</hi> Acts 20.28. Epheſ. 4.12, 13. 1 Pet. 5.2.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. <hi>That the onely materialls of which a true viſible Church of</hi> Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Chriſt <hi>doth conſiſt, and is made up of, is true matter, and true form,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:25867:8"/>Col. 2.5. <hi>that is to ſay, that all the matter or people ought to be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally Separated from the world, and all Antichrſtian Aſſemblies what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.15, 16, 17. Rev. 18.4. Seeing <hi>God</hi> in all ages put a viſible and diſtinct difference betwixt his <hi>people,</hi> and the men of the World, Lev. 20 29. Deut. 7.6. Act. 2.40. &amp; 19 9. of whom it is required that they be not onely <hi>beleevers,</hi> but alſo have a competent meaſure of <hi>knowledge</hi> to <hi>joyne, knit,</hi> and <hi>unite</hi> themſelves together in the comly <hi>order</hi> of the Goſpell, Deut. 29 9.10.12. Nehe. 10.28.29. Jer. 50.4. Act. 11.23, 24. And the reaſon why <hi>faith</hi> onely doth not make <hi>fit matter,</hi> is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that in the working of <hi>grace</hi> the ſoule is onely <hi>paſſive,</hi> and not <hi>active</hi> in the leaſt, <hi>faith</hi> being wrought in, or upon the <hi>ſoule</hi> by <hi>God</hi> alone. But in <hi>obedience</hi> a <hi>beleever</hi> is <hi>active,</hi> therfore it is required he ſhould be fitted with a meaſure of <hi>knowledge</hi> to tender that <hi>worship,</hi> and <hi>ſervice,</hi> which he offers up to <hi>God aright,</hi> and according to his <hi>will,</hi> otherwiſe it becomes <hi>will-worship,</hi> and a <hi>lame ſacrifice, which is the ſacrifice of fooles, in which God hath no delight, or pleaſure,</hi> Eccleſ. 5.1, 2.4. And the <hi>forme</hi> is that <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly State, City</hi> or <hi>Kingdome</hi> deſcribed in the Book of <hi>God,</hi> which hath diverſe, and ſeverall Names, as <hi>the beauty of holines,</hi> 1 Chro. 16.29. <hi>Syon,</hi> Pſal. 84.7. <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> Eſa. 62.6. <hi>the Lords holy Mountaine,</hi> Eſa. 65.9.11. <hi>his holy or ſecret place, which the Lord hath choſen to divell in,</hi> Pſal. 132.13, 14. <hi>Ieruſalem the mother of us all,</hi> Gal. 4.26. <hi>The City of the living God,</hi> Heb. 13.22 <hi>Mount Sion,</hi> Reve. 14.1. <hi>the beloved City,</hi> Reve. 20.9. <hi>the holy City, or new Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> Reve. 21.1, 2. <hi>the Lord is there,</hi> Ezek. 48.35. and that we are now as ſtrictly tyed to the <hi>inſtitutions</hi> of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpell, as the Jews were tyed to his <hi>inſtitutions</hi> under the Law, Acts 3.22, 23. Heb. 3.2.5. &amp; 10.28, 29 &amp; 12.25.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. <hi>That</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>in his new Teſtament never inſtituded no Nationall nor Provinciall, nor no univerſall Church, which then muſt needs have uniuerſall Officers, but onely particular Churches, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, many of which may be in one Kingdome or Province,</hi> 1 Cor. 16.1. 2 Cor. 8.1. Gal. 1.2.22. 1 Theſſ. 2.14. and all of them independant bodies, Rev. 1.2, 3 Chapters, and yet every one of them have one and the ſame <hi>ſtate,</hi> Gal. 4.26. one and the ſame <hi>King, head,</hi> and <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> one and the ſame <hi>Laws,</hi> one and the ſame manner of <hi>government;</hi> one and the ſame <hi>ordinance;</hi> one and the ſame <hi>inſtitutions,</hi> and manner of <hi>adminiſtrations;</hi> having all <hi>adminiſteriall power</hi> within themſelves, depending upon none; but onely upon <hi>Chriſt,</hi> their onely, and alone ſpirituall, and viſible head, 2 Cor. 11.2. Epheſ. 1.22, 23. and the 5.23.
<pb facs="tcp:25867:9"/>Col. 1.18.24. &amp; 2.19. who though he be <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> as the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, <hi>Lawes, government, worship, ordinances,</hi> and <hi>adminiſtrations</hi> are yet, is he viſible, Eſay 9.6, 7. Pſal. 110.12 Act. 7.55, 56. as well as his Kingdome, and all the <hi>Laws, ordinances,</hi> and <hi>admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations</hi> therof. And that it is altogether ſinfull, and unlawfull for any whatſoever to inflict any bodily or corporall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon any for <hi>ſpirituall things,</hi> or matters of <hi>conſcience</hi> (ſeeing <hi>excommunication,</hi> or <hi>caſting out</hi> into the world is now in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell put in the place of <hi>killing</hi> the <hi>body</hi> under the Law) which wicked practiſe notwithſtanding is not only uſed by the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolicall, and Satanicall <hi>Prelats</hi> here in <hi>England,</hi> but alſo by the Magiſtrates and Prieſts in New-<hi>England,</hi> who <hi>ungodly, wickedly,</hi> and ſinfully <hi>unpriſon, banish,</hi> and take away mens <hi>goods,</hi> and that even for <hi>Conſcience ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. <hi>That it is the duty of all thoſe that will approve their hearts unto</hi> God, <hi>and declare unto his people that they are his,</hi> Jam. 2 18 <hi>to walke in a ſpirituall totall Separation from the men of the world, by joyning themſelves freely and voluntarily to a true viſible Church, there pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely to worship and ſerve the Lord according to his own Laws, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and appointment, ſeeing the Lord never promiſed his preſence, bleſſing, peace, nor protection to any perſons whatſoever, but onely theſe that walke in this State, City, or Kingdome, into which all his people are bound in Conſcience to enter into it,</hi> Eſa. 26.20. Mat. 28.20. Cant. 1.6. that deſire according to their <hi>duty</hi> to <hi>glorifie him in the eyes of the world,</hi> by holding forth the <hi>publick profeſſion</hi> of the <hi>purity</hi> of his <hi>truth</hi> as ſo many <hi>burning and shining lamps in the midſt of a perverſe and crooked generation,</hi> Mat. 5.26. Phil. 2.15.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/>
               <hi>That it ſavours of a muddy, earthly, carnall, baſe, and unſanctified heart, for any man or woman whatſoever, be they high, or low rich, or poore, to plead that the people of God may lawfully walke in a ſtragling ſpirituall way, though they joyne not themſelves to a viſible Church,</hi> 1 Sam. 15.22, 23. Mat. 13.44, 45, 46.6.33. Mark. 10.22, 23. for the <hi>ſervants of God</hi> in former ages made no cavils againſt, (neither needed they any preſſing to) this <hi>duty,</hi> who with lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſires deſired to <hi>come before God,</hi> and meet with him in this his <hi>Sion,</hi> Pſal. 42.1, 2, 3. and 84.10. and who have taken this <hi>Kingdome of God by violence,</hi> Mat. 11.12. Act. 2.41. and that ſuch pleading doth declare that the chiefe treaſure of ſuch perſons are the empty huskes, and baſe things of this evill world, and that their hearts are poſſeſſed with <hi>ſelfe-ſeeking,</hi> and <hi>ſelfe ends,</hi> and <hi>covetouſneſſe which is Idolatry,</hi> Col. 3.5. Epheſ. 5.5. and have no regard to <hi>Gods glory,</hi> or <hi>honour,</hi> for which ſin he will plague
<pb facs="tcp:25867:9"/>them, 1 Sam. 2.30. Pſal. 2.12. eſpecially in their <hi>inward man,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 2.11.12. that they ſhall not excell in being famous amongſt the <hi>true children of Sion,</hi> for being eminent in the <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge</hi> of the <hi>true wayes and myſteries of God and godlineſse,</hi> Eſa 19. 13, 14. and 59 9, 10, 11, 12. Mal. 2 2. 1 Cor. 1.19. &amp; 3.19.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/>
               <hi>That Ieſus Chriſt did redeem, and ſave his people from the wrath to come, mainly and principally for this end, that they should glorifie him both in their ſoules and bodies without feare.</hi> Luk. 1.74. Joh. 14.21. 23. &amp; 15.8.10.14. 1 Cor. 6.19, 20. Rom. 12.1. which is done when they walke <hi>unblameably,</hi> and <hi>uprightly</hi> without any ſelfe-reſpects in his <hi>publike wayes;</hi> which it is their <hi>duty</hi> ſo to doe, Mark 10.30.33. in the worſt of times, and amongſt the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt oppoſitions whatſoever, Reve. 12.11. &amp; 14.1.4. though it be to <hi>the ſpoyling of their goods, and the loſing of their lives,</hi> Mat. 10. 37, 38, 39. ſeeing <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> will have his full, and whole <hi>price</hi> of all thoſe that will truly imbrace and entertain him, Zeche. 11.12. which is to part with all for his ſake and glory, with willingneſſe, and contentednes, Mat. 16.24, 25. Mark. 8.34 35.38. Luk. 9.23, 24 &amp; 14 16. whoſe <hi>praiſe</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> ought to be more precious and deare unto them, then all they have, are, or ſhall be, 1 Sam. 4.21, 22. Dan. 3.16, 17, 18. that is to ſay, then their own eternall happines and welfare. And that it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for any of <hi>Gods people</hi> to glorifie him aright, as they ſhould and ought to doe, till they be entered into, and joyned as <hi>fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Citizens</hi> with the <hi>Saints,</hi> Ephe. 2.19. in this <hi>heavenly State, City,</hi> or <hi>Kingdome,</hi> which he <hi>inſtituted</hi> and appointed principally <hi>for the perfecting and building up of the Saints,</hi> Ephe. 4.10.12, 13, 14. out of which they cannot poſſibly <hi>worship</hi> him aright, nor come to the true knowledge of the naked and pure wayes of <hi>God:</hi> ſeeing this City cannot be meaſured by any but thoſe that are within it. Therfore the <hi>peole of God</hi> according to his <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,</hi> Pſal. 110.3. Jere. 50.4, 5. ought with all willingneſſe, with longing and ſtriving deſires (without any compulcion) to come to <hi>worship God</hi> within this his <hi>Sion, Tabernacle and dwelling place,</hi> Pſal. 68.16. as his Saints in old time did, Pſa. 84.1, 2. &amp; 120.5. ſeeing here, and no where elſe he hath promiſed his <hi>preſence, with the increaſe, and growth in grace,</hi> Pſal. 9.11. &amp; 84.7. &amp; 92.13, 14. &amp; 133.3. Zeche. 8.3.12. and hath tyed all his <hi>worship</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, Joh. 4.23, 24. Lev. 17.1.2, 3, 4. 9. <hi>Therfore bleſſed are they that dwell in this his houſe, that they may be ſtill prayſing of him,</hi> Pſal. 84.4.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/>
               <hi>That it is as eaſie to prove that woman to be an honeſt woman, that hath had twenty Baſtards, as it is to prove the Nationall, or Parishionall
<pb facs="tcp:25867:10"/>Church, or Churches in</hi> England <hi>to be Chriſts true Spouſe,</hi> Reve. 13.16, 17. &amp; 16.19. <hi>And that they who by reaſon of blind and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant zeale offered their Children through the fire to the Devil, and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lech,</hi> Pſal. 101.37. Jer. 32.35. <hi>had as much ground and warrant for their ſo doing: as the members in the Church of</hi> England <hi>have for their worship and ſervice which they publikely tender up to God,</hi> Reve. 9.20, 21. &amp; 13.2.4. <hi>And that in the worship and ſervice of God there is nothing indifferent: but his commands doth ſtrictly tye us to punctuall obedience in all times, ages, and places; and that we muſt not in the leaſt have any reſpect to a miſinformed Conſcience,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 1.7, 8, 9, 10. <hi>which ſo farre as it falleth short of the word of God, is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſeeing it is to be guided by the revealed will of God,</hi> Deut. 29.29. Eſa. 8.20. 2 Chro. 5.15, 16, 17. <hi>and to be meaſured by it, and not it by a misguided, or erronious Conſcience,</hi> Mat. 22.29.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That though hearing in it ſelfe be a morrall thing, and though a falſe adminiſtration cannot deſtroy, nor annihilate any ordinance of God, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ordinance Maker, is the onely, and alone ordinance deſtroyer, and nullifier,</hi> Act. 6.14. <hi>yet hearing of the word preached from any falſe Officer whatſoever, is abſolutely unlawfull, becauſe it is a ſinfull commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicating, and partaking in his Adminiſtration, Office, or Inſtitution,</hi> Mat. 23.19, 20, 21, 22. compared with 1 Cor. 10.18. &amp; Mat. 10.40. Luk. 10.16. compared with Reve. 13.2.4. &amp; 1 Cor. 10.14.20, 21. 1 Joh. 5.21. Hoſ. 9.4. <hi>for he that partakes in any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration in a State, whether true, or falſe, partakes in the State it ſelfe:</hi> Therfore though the <hi>naked truth of God</hi> in the <hi>purity</hi> of it, were taught by <hi>falſe Officers,</hi> in <hi>falſe Aſſemblies,</hi> yet it is as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull for <hi>Gods people</hi> now to goe thither to pertake in <hi>hearing of it,</hi> or to <hi>eat</hi> any <hi>ſpirituall meat there,</hi> as it was for the Iſraelites to goe to the Philiſtims when the Arke of <hi>God</hi> was in the <hi>houſe</hi> of <hi>Dagon,</hi> there to ſeek <hi>Gods preſence:</hi> or for the Corinths to goe to the Idols Temple to <hi>eat</hi> of their <hi>ſacrifices</hi> there (though <hi>eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in it ſelfe be as <hi>morall</hi> as <hi>hearing</hi> is) yet the Corinths going thither to <hi>eat</hi> of their <hi>ſet apart,</hi> or <hi>inſtituted meat,</hi> made them to have <hi>communion</hi> with Devils, who were the <hi>inſtituters</hi> of their <hi>inſtitutions</hi> and <hi>ſtate,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.20, 21. and as lawfull was it for the Iſraelites to goe to <hi>Dan, Bethel</hi> or <hi>Gilgall,</hi> there to <hi>ſacrifice</hi> and doe <hi>worship</hi> unto <hi>God</hi> (as it is for us to goe to heare the <hi>word of God</hi> in <hi>falſe Aſſemblies</hi>) unto which places the <hi>Lord</hi> peremto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily commands them they ſhall not goe, Hoſ. 4.15. &amp; 9.15. Amos 5.5. ſeeing the <hi>Lord</hi> had tyed all his <hi>worship</hi> and <hi>ſervice</hi> to the Temple at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> and there onely promiſed his <hi>preſence</hi> and <hi>acceptance</hi> of their <hi>ſervice</hi> and <hi>worship,</hi> Deut. 12.11. 1 Kin. 8.
<pb facs="tcp:25867:10"/>compared with Chap. 9.2, 3. And that the <hi>Lord</hi> now under the Goſpell hath as ſtrictly tyed all his <hi>worship</hi> and <hi>ſervice</hi> to be offered up and performed in that <hi>heavenly State, City</hi> or <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> before ſpoken of, which is called the<note n="*" place="margin">Revel. 21.</note> 
               <hi>new Ieruſalem, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down from heaven; the name of which City is,</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">Ezek. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Lord is there.</hi> And therfore out of it to <hi>worship</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> may we not goe, leſt we ſin as the Jews did who left the Temple, and <hi>went to ſacifice under every green Tree,</hi> which though their <hi>ſacrifice</hi> which they offered up there was <hi>true ſacrifice,</hi> yet, it comes under a ſharpe reproof, as a groſſe and remarkable ſin; becauſe they brought it not to the <hi>true State</hi> and <hi>Altar,</hi> where onely the <hi>Lord</hi> had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to offer their <hi>ſacrifice.</hi> Even ſo though perſons goe to heare the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in a <hi>falſe ſtate,</hi> and think they may lawfully ſo do, yet they come under the ſame reproof with the Jews, being guilty of the ſame ſin, there being a true paralell betwixt the Jews offering up of <hi>ſacrifice</hi> under the Law, which was part of their <hi>worship,</hi> and of our <hi>hearing</hi> of the <hi>word</hi> preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which is part of our <hi>worship</hi> under the Goſpell; the <hi>materiall Temple</hi> at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> being the <hi>type,</hi> and our <hi>ſpirituall Ieruſalem,</hi> or <hi>heavenly State</hi> is the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of it, in the which onely, and alone, and no where elſe his <hi>people</hi> are to tender all their <hi>worship,</hi> and <hi>ſervice</hi> to him: ſeeing he hath not declared nor <hi>promiſed</hi> that he will own any <hi>ſervice</hi> whatſoever, but only that which is offered up unto him within this <hi>heavenly State</hi> or <hi>holy City,</hi> his <hi>dwelling</hi> and <hi>abiding place,</hi> of which <hi>glorious</hi> and excellent things in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal</hi> 87.3. <hi>Iſay.</hi> 60.19.20. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22. <hi>Chapters.</hi>
               </note> are ſpoken of. And that betwixt <hi>morrall</hi> things and <hi>inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions</hi> there is this difference: <hi>Morrall</hi> things are therfore <hi>good,</hi> becauſe they are ſo in themſelves. <hi>Inſtitutions</hi> are therfore <hi>good</hi> becauſe the <hi>inſtituter</hi> hath ſet them apart for a <hi>holy uſe,</hi> and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned them ſo to be; as the Tree in <hi>Paradice;</hi> and the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, and Temple, and all the things thereunto belonging, and all the <hi>inſtitutions</hi> under the Goſpell; as the <hi>Temple, Altar,</hi> and <hi>worshipers,</hi> all of which are <hi>inſtitutions</hi> and therfore <hi>holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That that Learning of Curious Arts and Sciences, which men at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain unto at the Schooles, is but Humane and not of God, the attaining unto which is no way neceſſary to the making of a man fit to beare office in the Church of</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">See for this, A late printed Booke, called. The Sufficiency of the Spirits Teaching with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Humane-Learning. By Sam. How.</note> Chriſt, <hi>but that man that wants them, may be every way as fit as he that hath them.</hi> For they puffe men up with <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>worldly wiſdome which is</hi>
               <note n="§" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19.20 27.28. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.1.4.6.13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.19.20.</note> 
               <hi>foolishneſſe, and enmity againſt God.</hi> And therfore thoſe that have theſe <hi>humane Arts,</hi> and <hi>earthly learning</hi> are not more unfit then others that want them, to be choſen by the Church of <hi>God officially</hi> to <hi>officiate</hi> therin, but Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they cannot eaſily be tryed according to thoſe <hi>rules</hi> which
<pb facs="tcp:25867:11"/>the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> layes down to <hi>Timothy</hi> for that end. For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>grace</hi> they will, and do cheat, couſen, and deceive the Saints many times with their Arts, by making that ſeem to be a <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall guift from God,</hi> which is nothing elſe but a <hi>humane Art.</hi> But that <hi>learning</hi> which chiefly makes the Saints fit to beare <hi>office</hi> in, and take care of the Church of <hi>God,</hi> is <hi>divine</hi> and <hi>ſpirituall learning,</hi> of which <hi>God</hi> is the<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.6.7 8.9.10.11.</note> Author, without which none are truly able to know, and interpret the <hi>holy</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10.11.14.</note> 
               <hi>Scripture.</hi> Therfore wo, wo. to all thoſe that follow, and are guided, and led by <hi>Antichriſts ignorant,</hi> and ſpirituall drunken Prieſts, whoſe ſoules are ſo infatuated, and beſotted with the abominable <hi>fornications</hi> of the <hi>Scarlet whore,</hi> that they are not able rightly to know the will of <hi>God,</hi> and therfore do they feed you with <hi>ashes, froth,</hi> and <hi>ſcumme,</hi> and theſe you take for famous <hi>truths,</hi> their hearts being ſo exceedingly deceived, that they are not able to deliver their ſoules from their groſſe abominable <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>wickednes,</hi> nor ſay <hi>is there not a lye in our right hand:</hi> for as the Prophet<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 44.18.</note> 
               <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>they have no knowledge nor heavenly underſtanding, for God hath shut their eyes, that they cannot ſee, &amp; their hearts that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not underſtand.</hi> Anſwer theſe 9. <hi>Propoſitions</hi> O all ye <hi>Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts,</hi> or <hi>Reformiſts,</hi> if your much boaſted of abilities, have any <hi>reality</hi> or <hi>ſubſtance</hi> in them beſides windie and cowardly brags, (who think you are <hi>ſeparated</hi> away frow <hi>Babilon</hi> and <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and yet you are in midſt of it and have <hi>communion</hi> with him) and by <hi>Gods</hi> aſſiſtance you ſhall be punctually replyed unto. But look to it, if you goe to your cowardly fugitive, and run-away Prieſts to get them to anſwere it, that you charge them not to ſtuffe their Books full with citations of their rotten, putrified and empty Fathers, and Authors, and Heatheniſh Poets, and Phyloſophers, which uſually they do, giving us three of them, for one well applyed place of <hi>Scripture.</hi> But if now they thus doe, of their Authority I ſhall no more eſteem, then of the <hi>dirt</hi> in the <hi>kennell:</hi> The moſt of whoſe Books are fit for no other uſe, or place, then to be burnt in the fire, as the Books of thoſe that uſed <hi>curious Arts</hi> in the<note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 19.19.</note> Apoſtles time were, and ſo ſhall the <hi>word of God grow, flourish,</hi> and <hi>prevaile</hi> as then it did. Neither let their anſwere be with tricks and quillets by the cunning of their deceivable <hi>humane Arts,</hi> with which they can make <hi>blacke</hi> ſeem <hi>white,</hi> juſt Jugler like; Nor yet with their rotten and falſe Scholaſticall diſtinctions, as hearing the <hi>word of God</hi> from an <hi>officer,</hi> and yet they doe not heare him as an Officer) which is but a Sophiſticall diſtinction ſerving to no purpoſe. And all theſe <hi>humane deviſes</hi> I eſteem of no more uſe in matters of <hi>controverſie</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:25867:11"/>to find out the naked <hi>truth</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> then <hi>pitch, roſen</hi> and <hi>flax</hi> is to quench fire, which will much more increaſe and aggravate it: even ſo will they, though things now ſhould be very darke, yet the making uſe of them to make them more obvious and <hi>cleare,</hi> will make them more miſty and obſcure. Therfore I deſire him, whoſoever he be that anſwers me, to weigh things in the ballance of the <hi>ſanctuary</hi> (I mean the unerring <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God</hi>) and to go to the Law and the Teſtimony, and ſpeak according to that, otherwiſe I ſhall tell him (and that in the words of the Spirit of <hi>God</hi>)<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 8.20.</note> 
               <hi>there is no light of truth in him.</hi> Therfore let it be anſwered by the Authority of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> for <hi>it is that which teſtifies of</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.39.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And the want of the true knowledge of this is the ground of all <hi>errour</hi> and<note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.29</note> 
               <hi>ignorance,</hi> which your Prieſts by their rotten filthy Diabolicall <hi>arts,</hi> and inventions do obſcure, darken, and ecclipſe. Therfore I doe verily think and beleeve that for this cauſe <hi>God</hi> will never <hi>honour</hi> them to doe him any ſpeciall or ſinguler piece of ſervice, <hi>for he taketh the wiſe in their own craftineſſe, and diſappointeth the deviſes of the crafty, and ſets up on high, thoſe that below,</hi>
               <note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.11.12.</note> 
               <hi>and maketh the wiſe men to perish,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 29.14.</note> 
               <hi>and fruſtrateth the tokens of lyars</hi> as they are) <hi>and maketh diviners mad, and turneth wiſe men backward, and maketh their knowledge "foolish,</hi> which by dayly, and large experience we ſee manifeſted, and made good, nor never make uſe of them, for principall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to pull down and deſtroy the filthy black: Soddomitiſt Babilonian Kingdome of <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> for as faſt as any of them by the <hi>word of God</hi> doe labour to pull it down with one hand, they by making uſe of their <hi>humane arts,</hi> and <hi>learning,</hi> build it up with both hands: and more ſtregthen the enemy with theſe their wicked <hi>weapons,</hi> then they weaken him with any other they can make uſe of. Therfore let all <hi>Gods people</hi> that deſire with all their might to pull down the <hi>whore, and make her deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, and naked;</hi> cry down all theſe <hi>wicked Arts,</hi> and <hi>human-learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and all worldly <hi>wiſdome</hi> to the pit of hell from whence they came, and only make uſe of the <hi>two-edged ſword</hi> of <hi>Gods word,</hi> as the very chief weapon to pierce and run through the very <hi>heart</hi> of the <hi>ſcarlet whore,</hi> and her upholders, for this will <hi>pierce even to the dividing aſunder of the ſoule and Spirit,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>and of the joynts and marrow,</hi> For the <hi>word of God</hi> is that <hi>two-edged ſword that comes out of the mouth of the Lamb our Captain</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>who ſits upon the white Horſe, who in righteouſneſſe and truth doth judge, and make war; and with this he goes forth conquering, and to conquer, and to ſmite the Nations and people that doe not, nor will not obey his truth, for he tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the winepreſſe of the fiercenes of the wrath of</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Almighty God.</hi> And
<pb facs="tcp:25867:12"/>with this <hi>ſpirituall, overcoming, unreſiſtable conquering weapon</hi> are we his Souldiers, or Armies, that are in <hi>heaven,</hi> or ſtand upon <hi>Mount Sion</hi> (that is, in the <hi>true Church,</hi> or <hi>ſtate of God</hi>) ready to do our Fathers will and pleaſure, to fight couragiouſly againſt our ſpirituall Babilonian enemies, <hi>in following the Lamb whither ſoever he goeth,</hi> and to do him what ſervice ſoever he pleaſeth to call us to, and not to love our lives unto the <hi>death;</hi> ſeeing he hath <hi>redeemed</hi> us from among <hi>men, and made us Kings and Prieſts unto God our Father.</hi> Therfore O my Brethren, be exhorted to <hi>cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage,</hi> and <hi>zeale,</hi> for the <hi>Lord</hi> and his <hi>truth:</hi> for this is it wherin he ſhall be <hi>glorified</hi> by us: therfore ſhake off all baſe, and carnall <hi>feare,</hi> and be not afraid of the <hi>greatnes</hi> of our <hi>enemies;</hi> but let us publikely in an united bond, profeſſe the <hi>purity</hi> of his <hi>truth</hi> in <hi>ſincerity,</hi> for we are ſure <hi>by the word of his</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.12.</note> 
               <hi>Teſtimony to overcome all that do oppoſe us:</hi> For the <hi>Lord</hi> ere long <hi>by the ſpirit of his mouth, and the brightnes of his coming,</hi> in this his glorious Kingdome (before ſpoken of) <hi>will deſtroy the man of ſin, that ſo long hath trampled this his holy City under foot,</hi> for the proſperity and flouriſhing of which we are bound in duty to ſtrain for, and hazard all we have. <hi>Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if I forget thee ô Ieruſalem, let my right hand forget her cunning; and if I doe not remember thee ô Sion let my tongue cleave to the roof of my mouth, yea if I prefer not</hi>
               <note n="§" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 137.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>Ieruſalem above my chief joy:</hi> For my ſoule longs, yea exceedingly with earneſt deſires to ſee <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> become (as I am ſure when <hi>Antichriſt</hi> is deſtroyed ſhe ſhall be) <hi>the prayſe of the whole earth.</hi> Therfore all ye <hi>choice Speare-men of the Lord,</hi> be as valiant for your <hi>God</hi> now in the dayes of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels <hi>tottering,</hi> as<note n="†" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.16, 17.</note> 
               <hi>Davids worthies</hi> was for him, and ſtoutly break through the Hoaſts of the Babilonians thoſe ſpirituall Phyli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims, and fetch, and take the <hi>water of life</hi> from out of their pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted hands, which they theeviſhly have ſtolen, and uſurpedly make uſe of, that the <hi>Lords</hi> weake ones may freely drink of it without feare of being poyſoned: and let us all, yea every one of us that ſtand upon <hi>Mount Sion</hi> with our Fathers name writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>in our</hi>
               <note n="“" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 50. <hi>&amp;</hi> 51. <hi>Reve.</hi> 18.</note> 
               <hi>foreheads</hi> according to our duty. Let us put our ſelvs in array againſt <hi>Babilon</hi> round about, and call together the <hi>Lords valiant Spearmen,</hi> and <hi>Archers</hi> againſt her. Therfore all ye that bend the Bow, Camp againſt her round about, and let none that belong unto her eſcape; <hi>but recompence her according to her worke, according to all that she hath done let us do unto her, for she hath been proud againſt the Lord, even againſt the holy one of Iſrael.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>let us cauſe her young men to fall in the ſtreets, and all her men of war let us</hi> (as much as we are able <hi>cut off.</hi> Now her <hi>choice men of war</hi> are her <hi>officers,</hi> whoſe <hi>offices</hi> is that great River <hi>Euphrates</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:25867:12"/>ſpoken of in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> which principally we muſt labour to dry up, becauſe till it be dryed up, <hi>we the ſons of righteouſneſſe, and Kings of the Eaſt cannot come to take her and deſtroy her.</hi> Now the chief meanes to dry up her <hi>offices,</hi> is to refuſe all ſpirituall ſubjection to them, and not to give to any of them at any time their uſurped fees, for this I will maintain, that it is abſolutely ſinfull, and unlawfull to pay unto them any money which they demand, as an Eccleſiaſticall right, or to enter bayl unto them: therfore in my judgement thoſe doe deny and diſhonour <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>truth,</hi> that directly or indirectly <hi>fee,</hi> or give money to their Diabollicall Purſevants, for their <hi>liberty</hi> when they are taken by them; ſure I am the Apoſtles and their followers were never ſo baſe and cowardly, yet this is a common ſinne amongſt all our Congregations, the <hi>Lord</hi> amend it: and in after time give us more <hi>courage</hi> and <hi>zeale</hi> for his <hi>glory,</hi> otherwiſe our condition will be like to <hi>Laodicea</hi> even to be <hi>luke-warme,</hi> for which we may ſhortly feare the <hi>Lord will ſpew us out of his mouth.</hi> A Second ſort of her Champions, are thoſe that draw nearer to <hi>God</hi> in many things then others of their Bretheren doe, and theſe are called <hi>Puritans</hi> or Profeſſours, whoſe vizards I have in part in my foregoing Propoſitions unmasked; and theſe by how much the more they ſeemingly draw nearer to <hi>God</hi> in their <hi>falſe wayes,</hi> ſo much the more hurt and miſchief they do, by keeping others more weaker then themſelves from a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſtooping intirely to the Scepter of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> for which ſinne the <hi>Lord</hi> plagues them: for it is dayly ſeen that even Publicans and Harlots enter into the Kingdome before them, to walke in that <hi>order</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath appointed for their <hi>building up,</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore againſt theſe ſhould we <hi>fight,</hi> and with all our ſtrength and cunning, take from them their <hi>masks, vizards,</hi> and <hi>figge-leaves,</hi> unto whom I may truly ſay as <hi>God</hi> by the Prophet<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay</hi> 47.</note> 
               <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaid to the old Babilonians, <hi>that your wiſdome, and your knowledge hath perverted you, which makes you ſay in your hearts you are well and need no mending. Therfore shall evill come upon you, and you shall not know from whence it ariſeth, and miſchief shall fall upon you and you shall not be able to put it off, and deſolation shall come upon you ſodainly, which you shall not know.</hi> Therfore ſtand now with your inchantments, and with the multitude of your <hi>ſervices</hi> (that is to ſay, with your tricks and quillets, and cunning ſoule-deceiving ſhifts) wherin you have laboured from your youth, if ſo be you ſhall be able to profit, and prevaile; you are wearied in the multitude of your Councels. Let now the Aſtrologers, the Starre-gazers, the monethly Prognoſticaters (that is to ſay, your famous Prieſts,
<pb facs="tcp:25867:13"/>thoſe <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>learned men</hi> (as you eſteem them) whoſe frothy ſavings, and fooliſh councell by ſome of you are judged as Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; let theſe I ſay ſtand up and <hi>ſave</hi> you (if they be able) from thoſe things that ſhall ſhortly come upon you, <hi>Behold they shall be as ſtubble, the fire shall burn them, and they shall not deliver them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the power of the flame therof, and there shall not be a coals for you to warme at, nor fire to ſet before you.</hi> Thus ſhall it be unto you with whom you have laboured, even your ſpirituall Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants from your <hi>youth,</hi> they ſhall wander every one to his quarter, none ſhall ſave you. <hi>O Iehovah thou Lord of hoſts, and powerfull God, that thou wouldeſt rend the heavens, that thou wouldſt in wrath and fury come down, that the Mountains might flow down at thy preſence, as when the melting fire burneth, even the fire that cauſeth the waters to layle, to make thy great, dreadfull, and terrible name known to thy Babilonian Antichriſtian adverſaries, that the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions therof may</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay.</hi> 64.1.2.</note> 
               <hi>tremble at thy preſence: and haſten thy coming in thy glorious Kingdome, and cauſe the brightnes therof to ſcorch, torment, and torture the very ſoules and ſpirits of thy ſpirituall enemies: and put</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 13.</note> Nehemiahs <hi>courage, and zeale into the hearts of all the Lambs redeemed ones, that they may at once power out the Vyalls of thy fury and fierce indignation</hi>
               <note n="‡" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>upon the very throne of the Beaſt, to the ruine therof, that his worshippers may gnaw their tongues for very pain, and cry out with weeping, and wayling for the deſtruction of their ſpirituall Babylon, alas, alas; and cauſe thy ſervants in all their ſpirituall battayles never to make uſe of any of the Beaſts foolishnes, or humane weapons, which are no better then bul-rushes; but make it known unto them that it is their duty to be as unlike unto him in all things whatſoever as ‡ poſſibly they can, and to keep cloſe to thy Law and Statutes,</hi> § For bleſſed are they that do thy Commandements, that they may have right to the Tree of life, and may enter in through the gates into the holy City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>And ſo my oppoſites I bid you farewell, and reſt yours in any ſervice for <hi>Chriſt</hi> his <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi> to be comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and truly deſiring the good and welfare of your ſoules, <hi>N. E.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25867:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
